<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd" []>
<concept id="mst-advising-committee">
  <title>Advisors and Advising Committees</title>
  <shortdesc></shortdesc>

  <prolog>
    <author type="creator">Graduate Program Committee</author>
    <copyright>
      <copyryear year="2014"/>
      <copyrholder>CS Department</copyrholder>
    </copyright>
  </prolog>
  <conbody>

<p>All graduate students have access to a faculty advisor who can help with both academic advising (i.e., issues related to getting a degree) and career advising. PhD students, and MS students under the thesis option, should select a faculty member to act as their research and course advisor as early as possible in their academic career and definitely by the time their plan of study is due (see <xref href="Plans%20of%20study.xml"/>). The advisor must be a full-time Virginia Tech faculty position with either a regular, emeritus, or courtesy appointment in the Department of Computer Science, and hold a Ph.D. or equivalent terminal degree.</p>

<p>In place of a single advisor, PhD or MS Thesis students can instead choose two faculty members to serve as co-advisors. In this case, at least one of the co-advisors must be a full-time Virginia Tech faculty position with either a regular, emeritus, or courtesy appointment in the Department of Computer Science, and hold a Ph.D. or equivalent terminal degree. The advisor or co-advisors chair the student’s advisory committee. </p>

<p>The composition of an M.S. thesis advisory committee must be designed taking into account the following considerations:</p>

<ul>
<li>The committee must have at least three members (including the advisor or co-advisors).</li>

<li>At least two members of the committee must hold a PhD or equivalent terminal degree. Any member without a PhD or equivalent terminal degree must have recognized expertise in their field and have research experience.</li>


<li>At least two members must hold tenure track or emeritus positions in the Department of Computer Science. </li>

<li>A person from outside the university can serve as an advisory committee member with the permission of the chair of the advisory committee. Note that outside members must be approved by the Graduate School, see section <xref href="Plans%20of%20Study.xml"/> for details.</li>
</ul>

<p>Ph.D. students and MS students who plan to do a thesis but who have not yet selected a research advisor or who need additional academic advising can approach any faculty member on the graduate program committee (GPC) to serve as an interim advisor, and who can serve to provide signatures and other official approvals as required. For most such students, the AGS serves as the de-facto interim advisor. </p>


  </conbody>
</concept>